msf.org 2019-04-12

# Privacy policy | Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) International

_Last updated on 26 June 2018_

## 1\. About this Privacy Notice

At MSF we make sure we protect the information you give us. References to “MSF”/“we”/“us”/”our” are to Médecins Sans Frontières International, 78 rue de Lausanne. Case Postale 10161211 Geneva 1. Switzerland.

  This privacy notice is written in accordance with relevant data protection legislation including the Swiss regulation on data protection and the General Data Protection Regulation. 

This privacy notice sets out how MSF International collects, uses and stores personal data via our international website (“Website”) www.msf.org. This Policy does not cover MSF’s presence on social media platforms such as, including but not limited to: Instagram, Youtube, Facebook, Google+, Linkedin, Twitter, Tumblr, Pinterest, Flickr, and on publishing platforms such as, including but not limited to: Issuu, Scribd, Medium on which we have established our own presence. In the context of those platforms, we are merely another user and the privacy policies as well as the terms and conditions of those platforms are applicable.  
If you’ve any questions please contact: Dataprotection.IO@geneva.msf.org

### When do we collect information about you? 

We collect information:

  * when you give it to us **directly**
  * when you give it to us **indirectly**
  * when you use our **website** , through **cookies**

_Directly_

  * Contacting MSF 
    * If you choose to contact us through contact information provided on our contact pages on the Website for any reason, we will collect the information you voluntarily provide to us. 
  * Applying for an International Office job 
    * We use a third party platform, Recruitee, to manage the information submitted by you when you apply for career opportunities with the International Office of MSF. Any information you submit through the form on our International Office page is provided by you to Recruitee and is also subject to [Recruitee’s privacy policy](https://recruitee.com/privacy). We have the right to access such Personal Information and process the Personal Information for the purposes as set out below.
  * Making a donation 
    * All donations are handled through the MSF office in your country of residence, or, if not possible in your country of residence, through an international donation platform maintained by Médecins Sans Frontières Hong Kong. The privacy policy of your local MSF office applies for a local MSF office in your country of residence, while the [privacy policy](https://donate.msf.org/policy.php?lang=en) of the international donation platform applies for the latter.  
  * We may automatically collect the following information with regard to each of your visits to the Website: 
    * Technical information, including the operating system and platform, browser type and version; and
    * Details of your visits to the Website, including but not limited to: every ‘HTTP Query’ your browser client sent to our server(s); the full Uniform Resource Locators (URL) clickstream to, through and from the Website (including date and time); page response times, download errors, length of visits to certain pages, page interaction information (such as scrolling, clicks, and mouse-overs), methods used to browse away from the page, traffic data, location data, weblogs and other communication data. This information does not identify you.

_Indirectly_

We may get your personal information via a fundraising organisation or platform if you’ve told them that you’re supporting MSF and with your consent. Please check their privacy policies when you give them your information.

  _Cookies_

  * Like most websites, our Website may place a “cookie” – a small text file – in the browser of your computer. This cookie will assign you a unique number that allows us to save your information so that the information does not need to be re-entered. Cookies can be either “persistent” or “session” based. Our Website uses both types of cookies.
  * Persistent cookies are stored on your computer, contain an expiration date (by default the cookies expire after 23 days), and may be used to track your browsing behaviour upon return to the issuing website or component (such as plugins or embedded media, e.g., a YouTube video embedded on our website). You can remove persistent cookies by following directions provided in your internet browser’s “Help” menu.
  * Session cookies are short-lived, are used only during a browsing session, and expire when you quit your browser.
  * You may refuse to accept cookies by activating the setting on your browser which allows you to refuse the setting of cookies. Instructions on how to do so will vary from browser to browser but you can find out more at www.aboutcookies.org. Some features and functionality may be lost if you choose to disable cookies. Also, remember that you will have to adjust the cookie settings for each browser and device and you use to visit our Website.
  * Our Website may contain links to other sites that may use cookie technology. We do not have access to, or control over, these cookies.

What cookies do we use?

  * Google Analytics 
    * We use Google analytics to see how our site is performing e.g. what articles are read, how many donations we receive and where visitors come from. The full list of Google Analytics cookies are below. Google analytics collects no personal data or IP addresses.
  * Google Optimize 
    * We use Google Optimize to help us understand how visitors engage with our website, e.g. which page designs work or what routes visitors take to apply for a job. Google Optimize collects no personal data or IP addresses.
  * Google Adwords 
    * We use Google Adwords to help us create more targeted adword campaigns, these are the adverts you see in search results.
  * Facebook 
    * We use Facebook to see if our paid Facebook campaigns are effective. It also helps us find out if we’re talking to the right people. This is done in accordance with Facebook’s policies. You can read more about Facebook’s policies here.

## 2\. What information do we collect?

If you contact us through the information provided on our contact pages we'll usually collect your:

  * Email 

## 3\. How do we use your information

As a general rule, your personal data will not be used for any other purpose than those for which they were voluntarily provided to us. Your personal data are shared or transferred to third parties if such sharing or transfer is authorised by you or required to achieve the purposes for which you have provided them to us. It means that we may share your personal data with service providers, who help assist us in fulfilling our purposes. Personal data may also be shared with third parties when required by law or by a court order. 

Your Personal Information may be used in the following ways:

  * If you have contacted us via the contact details provided on our Website, we will use the information you have provided, including your email address, to respond to your inquiry.
  * Any Personal Information you submit when applying for career opportunities will be used solely for recruitment purposes (including for identifying job applicants, evaluating applications, making hiring and employment decisions, and contacting you by phone or in writing).
  * Your information may also be used for technical purposes, including: 
    * To ensure that content from the Website is presented in the most effective manner for you and for your computer
    * statistical purposes; and
    * analyse our fundraising activity

###  How we use your data depends on why you’re providing it

_Surveys_

We use surveys to understand who visits our websites and how they use it, helping us to create better content for you and make our websites easier to use.  
We may ask for your email address if you’re happy to be involved in future surveys or testing. We’ll only use this to ask you to help us with these types of requests.

## 4\. Who has access to your data

### Trained staff

Your information is only accessible by trained staff. We regularly review who has access to your information. As a general rule, your personal data will only be accessible insofar as it is necessary to fulfill the purpose for which it was collected. For instance, the data you provide for donations will be accessible to our donations department, our fundraising and marketing team and to service providers, if any, for the purpose of processing your donation. We do comprehensive checks on any contractors before we work with them. We always put a contract in place that sets out how they manage the personal data they collect or have access to.

### Disclosure of information

We will never share your Personal Information with any other company or third party without your consent, except in the following circumstances (each as permitted by applicable law, in particular, with regard to a transfer out of the EEA, as applicable):

  * as set out in this Policy;
  * when we are required to do so by law, for example, in response to a subpoena, in response to a court order or other legal obligation, or in response to a valid request from a law enforcement agency;
  * to protect the security or confidentiality of our records and systems;
  * in special cases when we have reason to believe that disclosing this information is necessary to identify, contact, or bring legal action against someone who may be causing injury to or interference with our rights, or
  * in the event that we sell or transfer all, or any portion of, our business or assets (including in the event of any reorganisation, dissolution, spin-off, or liquidation) we reserve the right to transfer your Personal Information to the relevant acquirer, successor, purchaser or beneficiary, or any appropriate combination of them.

We operate globally and may have a need to transfer certain Personal Information to countries outside the EEA which do not provide an adequate level as required under EU data protection law. We use Standard Contractual Clauses to ensure that your Personal Information is adequately protected and your privacy respected in the case of such a transfer.

## 5\. How do we keep your information safe?

  * We use reasonable precautions to protect your Personal Information and to store it securely. Our Website has a secure SSL certificate, a global standard security technology that enables encrypted communication between the web browser and the web server.
  * Unfortunately, the transmission of information via the internet is not completely secure. We will do our best to protect your Personal Information, but cannot guarantee the security of your information transmitted to our Website; any transmission is at your own risk.

## 6\. How long do we keep your information? 

We keep your information for as long as it’s necessary in connection with the purposes defined above in “How do we use your information?”.

If you request to receive no further contact from us, we'll keep only the basic information about you on our suppression list in order to avoid sending you unwanted materials in the future, for the duration allowed by the application legislation. 

## 7\. Our legal basis for processing personal data

Organisations need a lawful basis to collect and use personal data under data protection law. The law allows for six ways to process personal data (and additional ways for sensitive personal data). Three of these are relevant to the types of processing that MSF carries out: 

  * A person’s consent (eg to send you direct marketing by e-mail or SMS);
  * Processing that is necessary for compliance with a legal obligation (eg to process a gift aid declaration); and 
  * Our legitimate interests (please see below for more information). 

Our legitimate interests may include:

  * **Charity Governance;** including delivery of our charitable purposes, statutory and financial reporting and other regulatory compliance purposes;
  * **Administration and operational management;** including responding to solicited enquires, providing information and services, research, events management, the administration of volunteers and employment and recruitment requirements. 

If you'd like to change our use of your personal data in this manner, please get in touch with us using the details above.

## 8\. How can you change your information and what are your rights?

Contact us at Dataprotection.IO@geneva.msf.org if you'd like to change or update your personal information. 

  You have a **number of rights** under data protection legislation:

  * You can request any information we hold on you. Email us at Dataprotection.IO@geneva.msf.org and ask for it in writing. You may be asked for proof of identity.
  * You have the right to ask us to stop using or to restrict the processing of your personal data.
  * You can withdraw your consent to us processing your data at any time (where such processing is based on consent eg to send you electronic direct marketing).
  * If you believe our records are inaccurate you have the right to ask for those records concerning you to be updated. To update your records please get in touch with us using the details above.
  * In accordance with the provisions of the General Data Protection Regulation, you have a right to erasure (“to be forgotten” i.e. to have your personal data deleted from our database), or transferred to another organisation (“data portability”). 
  * If you have any concerns about the way your data is being used or if you’d like to make a complaint, please contact us using the details above.
  * You are entitled to file a complaint about how MSF treats your data. To do so, you may directly contact: Préposé Fédéral à la Protection des Données et à la Transparence (PFPDT), Feldeggweg 1, CH-3003 Berne (tel.: +41 (0)58 462 43 95).

## 9\. When do we update this notice? 

We change this Privacy Notice when we need to. If we make any significant changes in the way we treat your personal information we’ll make this clear on our websites or by contacting you directly.

**Last updated on 26 June 2018**

Any all rights on this document belong to MSF. Any reproduction, without written consent, is strictly forbidden.
